A Guide to the Foundation for Child Development (Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City) records FA405
Rockefeller Archive Center
Foundation for Child Development (Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City) records
1904-1915, 1919-1920, 1931-1933
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Lash, Trude W.
Brim, Orville Gilbert, 1883-1987
Bronfenbrenner, Urie, 1917-2005
Association for the Aid of Crippled Children
Kagan, Jerome
Emmet, Jessie K.
Wheatley, George M.
Richardson, Stephen A.
Foundation for Child Development
Valdivieso, Rafael (Ray)
Takanishi, Ruby
Hecht, George J.
Blum, Barbara B.
Hetherington, E. Mavis (Eileen Mavis), 1926-
Zill, Nicholas
Dollard, Charles, 1907-1977
Clinton, Hillary Rodham
Hunter-Gault, Charlayne
Birch, Herbert George
Cuyler, Lewis Baker
Swinyard, Chester A.
Senn, Milton J. E.
Kamerman, Sheila B.
Moore, Evelyn
Rockefeller, Mary French
Sigal, Heidi
FA405
1 Microform Reels
Biographical/Historical note
The Foundation for Child Development had its origins in the Guild for the Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City (the Guild), an organization whose mission was to "care for the physical, social, domestic, educational, economic, and spiritual conditions of these unfortunates." It became the Association for the Aid of Crippled Children (AACC) in 1908, when it was established in New York City as a voluntary agency that sought to teach and aid disabled children who were victims of polio.
In the early twentieth century, physically disabled children were often homebound with no access to formal education. Mabel Irving Jones, a concerned citizen and advocate for these youngsters, provided the impetus behind the creation and eventual incorporation of an agency operating under the auspices of the New York City Children's Aid Society. By 1904 nearly 120 disabled school-aged children were attending school outside of the home; in 1906, Public School 104 of the New York City Board of Education operated the first public school class for crippled children. The Guild sought to treat those children neglected by hospitals and clinics and the "hundreds of chronic cases of crippled children whom these charities do not and cannot reach." The Guild cooperated with churches and other social services organizations including St. John's Guild, the Henrietta Industrial School, and the Hartley House Settlement, to teach children outside of the home, provide a luncheon meal, and return them to their homes. The Guild’s second Annual Report in 1898 indicated that this is the "first systematic effort ever made in New York City to give the crippled children out of institutions a helpful education."
Separated from the Children's Aid Society in 1908, the AACC was supported entirely by contributions and employed a staff of ten, led by trained nurses. In addition to providing transportation to school and health clinics and braces and other therapeutic devices, the AACC also established physical rehabilitation facilities. By 1940, over 30,000 children had benefited from these services, including children with cerebral palsy and other disorders of fetal and neonatal origin.
The organization’s early focus on the needs of a stranded school-aged population firmly defined its legacy. In later years, similar enterprises supported direct-care and research to benefit adult rehabilitation. The AACC joined with New York University-Bellevue Hospital to establish the Children's Division of the Institute of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, today known as the Rusk Institute. During World War II, their pioneering work helped to rehabilitate injured soldiers.
In 1972 the Association changed its name to the Foundation for Child Development (FCD) to reflect its role as a grant-making organization and in particular its evolved focus on child development. Included within its mission were goals of preventing child poverty and promoting the economic stability of families.
The Foundation for Child Development is a national private philanthropy dedicated to the principle that all families should have the social and material resources to raise their children to be healthy, educated, and productive members of their communities. The Foundation seeks to understand children, particularly the disadvantaged, and to promote their well-being. They believe that families, schools, nonprofit organizations, businesses, and government at all levels share complementary responsibilities in the critical task of raising new generations.
Conditions Governing Access note
Records are open for scholarly research without restriction.
Related Archival Materials note
Related materials may be found in:
The Foundation for Child Development records (RAC); the Leonard Mayo papers, at the University of Minnesota, Twin Cities; the New York City Board of Education records, at Teachers College, Columbia University; and in the Russell Sage Foundation records (RAC); the Social Science Research Council records (RAC); and the William T. Grant Foundation records (RAC).
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Other Finding Aids
FA019 Foundation for Child Development records
Existence and Location of Originals
Microfilm Reel 1 is a copy obtained by the Rockefeller Archive Center from the University of Minnesota.
The original Board of Managers's Minutes and Secretary's Book of the Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City for the years 1904-1915, 1919-1920, 1931-1933, was microfilmed by the University of Minnesota, Twin Cities in 1965.
Requests for copies of the microfilm should be directed to the University of Minnesota.
Public policy; Public health; Philanthropy; Social service; New York (N.Y.); Medical care; Philanthropy -- United States; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Child development; Charities; Lash, Trude W.; Brim, Orville Gilbert, 1883-1987; Bronfenbrenner, Urie, 1917-2005; Association for the Aid of Crippled Children; Kagan, Jerome; Emmet, Jessie K.; Wheatley, George M.; Richardson, Stephen A.; Foundation for Child Development; Valdivieso, Rafael (Ray); Takanishi, Ruby; Hecht, George J.; Blum, Barbara B.; Hetherington, E. Mavis (Eileen Mavis), 1926-; Zill, Nicholas; Dollard, Charles, 1907-1977; Clinton, Hillary Rodham; Hunter-Gault, Charlayne; Birch, Herbert George; Cuyler, Lewis Baker; Swinyard, Chester A.; Senn, Milton J. E.; Kamerman, Sheila B.; Moore, Evelyn; Rockefeller, Mary French; Sigal, Heidi
- Administration, 1904-1915, 1919-1920, 1931-1933; bulk
  Arrangement note
  This material is predominantly arranged chronologically.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
  The archival material has been reformatted and the original records are not available. User copies of the microfilm are available for scholarly access.
  - Administration - Board of Directors Meetings, 1904-1915, 1919-1920, 1931-1933; bulk
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - 'Secretary's Book', 1904-1914, 1919-1920, 1931-1933 (Reel 1, Frame 1)
    - Annual Meeting of the Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City, November 28, 1904 (Reel 1, Frame 2)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, November 28, 1904 (Reel 1, Frame 3)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, January 23, 1905 (Reel 1, Frame 4)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, February 27, 1905 (Reel 1, Frame 5)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, March 27, 1905 (Reel 1, Frame 6)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, April 25, 1905 (Reel 1, Frame 7)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, May 15, 1905 (Reel 1, Frame 8)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Special Board of Managers' Meeting - Minutes, October 2, 1905 (Reel 1, Frame 9)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, October 23, 1905 (Reel 1, Frame 10)
    - Annual Meeting of the Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City, November 27, 1905 (Reel 1, Frame 11)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, November 27, 1905 (Reel 1, Frame 12)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, December 26, 1905 (Reel 1, Frame 13)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, February 26, 1906 (Reel 1, Frame 14)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, March 26, 1906 (Reel 1, Frame 15)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, April 30, 1906 (Reel 1, Frame 16)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, May 28, 1906 (Reel 1, Frame 17)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, October 29, 1906 (Reel 1, Frame 18)
    - Annual Meeting of the Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City, November 24, 1906 (Reel 1, Frame 19)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, November 24, 1906 (Reel 1, Frame 20)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, January 7, 1907 (Reel 1, Frame 21)
      Scope and Contents note
      The year that is written on the page in 1906.
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, January 27, 1907 (Reel 1, Frame 22)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, February 25, 1907 (Reel 1, Frame 23)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, March 25, 1907 (Reel 1, Frame 24)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, c. April-August, 1907 (Reel 1, Frame 25)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, September 15, 1907 (Reel 1, Frame 26)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, October 28, 1907 (Reel 1, Frame 27)
    - Annual Meeting of the Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City, November 25, 1907 (Reel 1, Frame 28)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, November 25, 1907 (Reel 1, Frame 29)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, January 28, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 30)
      A Board of Managers Meeting was called for February 24, 1908, but this meeting was not held.
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, March 30, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 31)
    - Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City - Board of Managers Meeting - Minutes, May 25, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 32)
    - Special Meeting of the Board of Managers of the Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City, November 23, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 33)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, February 25, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 34)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Constitution, Amendments and By-Laws, undated (Reel 1, Frame 35)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, February 20, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 36)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, March 19, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 37)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, April 24, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 38)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, May 21, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 39)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, October 15, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 40)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, November 19, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 41)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Special Meeting, November 20, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 42)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, December 17, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 43)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, January 21, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 44)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, February 18, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 45)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, March 18, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 46)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, April 15, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 47)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, May 20, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 48)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, October 21, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 49)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, November 18, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 50)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee - Minutes, December 1, 1910 (Reel 1, Frame 51)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, February 6, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 52)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, March 5, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 53)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, April 2, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 54)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Special Meeting - Minutes, May 12, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 55)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, October 8, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 56)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Special Meeting - Minutes, November 5, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 57)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, November 5, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 58)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, December 3, 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 59)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, January 6, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 60)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, February 4, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 61)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, March 4, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 62)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, April 1, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 63)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, May 6, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 64)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, October 15, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 65)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, November 4, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 66)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Special Meeting - Minutes, November 8, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 67)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, December 2, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 68)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, January 6, 1910 (Reel 1, Frame 69)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, February 3, 1910 (Reel 1, Frame 70)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, March 3, 1910 (Reel 1, Frame 71)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Special Meeting - Minutes, March 11, 1910 (Reel 1, Frame 72)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, April 7, 1910 (Reel 1, Frame 73)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, May 5, 1910 (Reel 1, Frame 74)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Special Meeting - Minutes, May 19, 1910 (Reel 1, Frame 75)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, October 6, 1910 (Reel 1, Frame 76)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, November 3, 1910 (Reel 1, Frame 77)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Special Meeting - Minutes, November 17, 1910 (Reel 1, Frame 78)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, December 1, 1910 (Reel 1, Frame 79)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, January 4, 1911 (Reel 1, Frame 80)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Special Meeting - Minutes, January 11, 1911 (Reel 1, Frame 81)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, February 2, 1911 (Reel 1, Frame 82)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, March 1, 1911 (Reel 1, Frame 83)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, April 6, 1911 (Reel 1, Frame 84)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, May 4, 1911 (Reel 1, Frame 85)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, October 5, 1911 (Reel 1, Frame 86)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, November 2, 1911 (Reel 1, Frame 87)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Special Meeting - Minutes, December 7, 1911 (Reel 1, Frame 88)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, December 7, 1911 (Reel 1, Frame 89)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, January 4, 1912 (Reel 1, Frame 90)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, February 2, 1912 (Reel 1, Frame 91)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, March 7, 1912 (Reel 1, Frame 92)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, April 4, 1912 (Reel 1, Frame 93)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, May 2, 1912 (Reel 1, Frame 94)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, October 3, 1912 (Reel 1, Frame 95)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, November 7, 1912 (Reel 1, Frame 96)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Special Meeting - Minutes, December 5, 1912 (Reel 1, Frame 97)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, December 5, 1912 (Reel 1, Frame 98)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, January 2, 1913 (Reel 1, Frame 99)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, February 6, 1913 (Reel 1, Frame 100)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, March 6, 1913 (Reel 1, Frame 101)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, April 6, 1913 (Reel 1, Frame 102)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, May 8, 1913 (Reel 1, Frame 103)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, October 2, 1913 (Reel 1, Frame 104)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, November 6, 1913 (Reel 1, Frame 105)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, December 4, 1913 (Reel 1, Frame 106)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, January 8, 1914 (Reel 1, Frame 107)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, February 5, 1914 (Reel 1, Frame 108)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, March 5, 1914 (Reel 1, Frame 109)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, April 9, 1914 (Reel 1, Frame 110)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, May 14, 1914 (Reel 1, Frame 111)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, October 8, 1914 (Reel 1, Frame 112)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, December 9, 1914 (Reel 1, Frame 113)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, January 13, 1915 (Reel 1, Frame 114)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, February 10, 1915 (Reel 1, Frame 115)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, March 8, 1915 (Reel 1, Frame 116)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, April 14, 1915 (Reel 1, Frame 117)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Board of Directors - Minutes, May 13, 1915 (Reel 1, Frame 118)
    - Correspondence Regarding the Merger of the Guild for Crippled Children of the Poor of New York City and the Association for the Aid of Crippled Children, October-November 1908 (Reel 1, Frame 119)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Annual Meetings - Minutes, November 11, 1909 (Reel 1, Frame 120)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Annual Meetings - Minutes, November 10, 1910 (Reel 1, Frame 121)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Annual Meetings - Minutes, November 9, 1911 (Reel 1, Frame 122)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Annual Meetings - Minutes, November 14, 1912 (Reel 1, Frame 123)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Annual Meetings - Minutes, November 13, 1913 (Reel 1, Frame 124)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Annual Meetings - Minutes, November 12, 1914 (Reel 1, Frame 125)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Minutes of the Board of Directors, October 8, 1914 (Reel 1, Frame 126)
    - Correspondence Regarding the November 11, 1914 Association for the Aid of Crippled Children Board of Directors Meeting, undated (Reel 1, Frame 127)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Financial Documents, 1915 and 1919 (Reel 1, Frame 128)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, February 11, 1919 (Reel 1, Frame 129)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, March 17, 1919 (Reel 1, Frame 130)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, April 9, 1919 (Reel 1, Frame 131)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, May 13, 1919 (Reel 1, Frame 132)
    - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, June-October 1919 (Reel 1, Frame 133)